1909 Hudson-Fulton Celebration Collection
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
- 8. Badges, Medals, and Pins, 1909; 12.0 linear feet 12 Box (Box 10 -, Box 22)
  - Subseries 8.1: Badges and Medals, 1909; 10.0 linear feet 10 Box (Box 10 -, Box 20)
    - Hudson-Fulton Banquet Hudson Medal, Spot of damage at top of case and two much smaller spots along bottom of top cover. (Box 10)
      Black outer case with green interior. Case reads “Hudson Fulton Banquet/ September 29, 1909.” Obverse of medal depicts Henry Hudson and sailors aboard “Half-Moon”. Top reads “Discovery of Hudson River by Henry Hudson A.D. MDCIX,” bottom left reads “The American Numismatic Society,” bottom right reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration Comm.,” bottom reads “Half Maene”. Reverse of medal depicts three female figures representing Steam Navigation, History, and Commerce below a portrait of Robert Fulton. The background features views of New York in 1807 and 1909. Below image reads “First Use of Steam Navigation/ On The Hudson River/ 1807”. Metal designed by Emil Fuchs, whose name is signed in the bottom corner of each image.
    - HF Celebration Sterling Silver Official Medal of Commission, Toning along edges of each face, obverse and reverse, of medal. (Box 11)
    - HF Celebration Bronze Official Medal of Commission, Dark spots of tarnish across center to bottom of reverse and around edges of obverse. Potential chips and indentations in outer edge. Small spots of patina on outer edge. (Box 11)
      Bronze medal featuring Henry Hudson and sailors aboard “Half-Moon” on obverse. Obverse reads “Discovery of Hudson River by Henry Hudson A.D. MDCIX,” bottom left reads “The American Numismatic Society,” bottom right reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration Comm.,” bottom reads “Half Maene”. Reverse of medal depicts three female figures representing Steam Navigation, History, and Commerce below a portrait of Robert Fulton. The background features views of New York in 1807 and 1909. Reverse reads “First Use of Steam Navigation/ On The Hudson River/ 1807”. Metals designed by Emil Fuchs, whose name is signed in the bottom corner of each image on obverse and reverse. Small hole drilled into top edge of medal. Bronze medals were made available for purchase to the public.
    - HF Celebration Bronze Official Medal of Commission #2 (Box 11)
    - HF Celebration Bronze Official Medal of Commission #3, Small spots of tarnish along top edge of image. Tarnish across reverse. Small spot of rust on reverse center. (Box 11)
    - Hudson-Fulton Citizens’ Comm. Medal, Medal has tarnished. Ribbon is frayed along edges and slightly discolored. Patina across lettering on top bar. Top layer of case cover has worn away along bottom of front edges. (Box 12)
      Bronze medal featuring Dutch flag as ribbon. Top bar reads “Citizens’ Comm.”. Obverse features image of Lady Columbia holding the “Half-Moon” and “Clermont” in each hand with background of NYC skyline. Edges read “Hudson-Fulton/ Celebration”. Reverse features portraits of Hudson and Fulton. Edges read “Henry Hudson 1609/ Robert Fulton 1807/ 1909”. Outer case features leather cover and fabric within. Top inside cover stamped with “Medallic/ Art Company/ New York/ U.S.A. Front cover reads “The/ Hudson-Fulton/ Celebration/ Commission”.
    - Hudson-Fulton Commission Medal, Medal has slightly tarnished. Longer ribbons are slightly frayed along edges and slightly discolored. Outer case has two small areas of damage: one on front right and on back, center of cover. Inside top of case features faint staining. Outer storage box features frayed edges and corners and discoloration. Potential water damage to outer box, as well. Hinge of case has beginnings of rust and patina. (Box 12)
      Medal, possibly made of silver, featuring Dutch flag as ribbon with additional longer ribbons. Top bar reads “Commission”. Obverse features image of Lady Columbia holding the “Half-Moon” and “Clermont” in each hand with background of NYC skyline. Edges read “Hudson-Fulton/ Celebration”. Reverse features portraits of Hudson and Fulton. Edges read “Henry Hudson 1609/ Robert Fulton 1807/ 1909”. Outer case features leather cover and fabric within. Front cover reads “The/ Hudson-Fulton/ Celebration/ Commission”. Top inside cover stamped with “Medallic/ Art Company/ New York/ U.S.A. Case stored in purple box. Inside top lid stamped with “Medallic/ Art Company/ New York/ U.S.A.
    - Hudson-Fulton Citizens’ Comm. Medal #2, Faint staining across inner top of case. Possible dust on inside to right of medal. Ribbon is slightly discolored. Front cover has some wear in center and small scratch on upper right. Outer storage box has various small scratches across front. Edges and corners of box frayed. Hinge of case rusted. (Box 12)
      Bronze medal featuring Dutch flag as ribbon. Top bar reads “Citizens’ Comm.”. Obverse features image of Lady Columbia holding the “Half-Moon” and “Clermont” in each hand with background of NYC skyline. Edges read “Hudson-Fulton/ Celebration”. Reverse features portraits of Hudson and Fulton. Edges read “Henry Hudson 1609/ Robert Fulton 1807/ 1909”. Outer case features brown cover and fabric within. Front cover reads “The/ Hudson-Fulton/ Celebration/ Commission”. Top inside cover stamped with “Medallic/ Art Company/ New York/ U.S.A. Front cover reads “The/ Hudson-Fulton/ Celebration/ Commission”. Inside top lid stamped with “Medallic Art CO/ New York/ U.S.A.
    - Hudson-Fulton Commission Medal #2, Faint staining across inner top of case. Joint has begun to separate and fray. Slight fraying of edges of ribbon. Medal is slightly discolored. Outer box contains water damage on cover. Various scratches on outer box. Edges and corners are frayed. Bottom of top of box is torn. Hinge of case rusted. (Box 12)
    - Hudson-Fulton Celebration Public Health and Safety Committee Badge, Outer case is torn along bottom of top. Cracks along top and bottom edge of top of cover. Tear in top cover right edge. Faint staining along edges of case. Small stain on back right of case. Ribbon slightly discolored. Medal and top bar tarnished. (Box 12)
      Medal featuring Dutch flag as ribbon. Ribbon reads “Public Health/ and/ Safety”. Top bar reads “Commission”. Obverse of metal features portrait of Hudson and Fulton and the dates “1609” and “1909”. Reverse features female image in temple-style building over Hudson-Fulton Celebration ships sailing on Hudson River. Reverse reads “Oct 1909/ Newburgh”. Outer case is green with white outline. Inside of top of cover reads “Committee Badge/ Hudson-Fulton Celebration/ Newburgh, N.Y.”
    - Official Medal of Hudson Fulton Celebration Commission, Wearing of wood in corners. Small scratches down left side of wooden plaque. Screws attaching medals and hanging hardware to plaque have rusted. Small scratches along side edges. (Box 12)
      Two medals within wooden plaque. Top medal depicts Henry Hudson and sailors aboard “Half-Moon”. Top reads “Discovery of Hudson River by Henry Hudson A.D. MDCIX,” bottom left reads “The American Numismatic Society,” bottom right reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration Comm.,” bottom reads “Half Maene”. Bottom medal depicts three female figures representing Steam Navigation, History, and Commerce below a portrait of Robert Fulton. The background features views of New York in 1807 and 1909. Below image reads “First Use of Steam Navigation/ On The Hudson River/ 1807”. Metals designed by Emil Fuchs, whose name is signed in the bottom corner of each image. Metals given to colleges and secondary schools through the New York State Education Department in 1909.
    - Official Medal of Hudson Fulton Celebration Commission #2, Wearing of wood in corners. Fraying of wood around medals in upper right. Faint scratches along bottom edge of front. Very small chips in wood along right edge. Small crack on back bottom center. Small scratches along side edges. Screws attaching medals and hanging hardware to plaque have rusted. Pasted paper on back cracking and missing small portions—explanation on medals still legible. Residue from glue on wood around paper’s edges. (Box 12)
    - Official Medal of Hudson Fulton Celebration Commission #3, Wearing of wood in corners. Significant scratches along back edges of plaque. Small scratches along side edges. Screws attaching medals and hanging hardware to plaque have rusted. Wood discolored around top medal and along top of bottom medal. (Box 12)
    - Circle of Friends of the Medallion Medal One, Edges of cover has begun to fray. Small areas of discoloration on front cover in bottom left and center. Upper left corner of embossed logo has faded away. Inside leaves’ edges are discolored. Very small stain in bottom right corner of front cover. Small stain on upper spine and on back cover upper left. Small crease in top of spine. (Box 12)
      Clothbound book-style presentation case featuring historical background on Hudson and Fulton’s journeys up the Hudson River. Cover features gold embossed logo of Circle of Friends of the Medallion with portrait of Pisanello at upper right of cover and number “1” on upper section of spine. Center of case contains bronze die-struck Hudson-Fulton Celebration commemorative medal issued by the Circle of Friends of the Medallion. The medal was the first in the series issued in 1909. The medal was designed and cast by John Flanagan (1865-1962). Front of metal features images of Hudson and Fulton. Obverse reads Henry Hudson/ Robert Fulton/ MDCIX”. Reverse of metal features image of female figure lying upon clouds, holding a lightbulb to symbolize the age of electricity. In the background are the “Half-Moon” and “Clermont” on the Hudson River before the New York City skyline. Back reads “MDCIX MDCCCVII/ MDCIX”. Medal and case are accompanied by papers regarding its history.
    - HF Celebration Small Silver-plated Official Suspension Medal, Medal features dark tarnish across both faces and much of plating has been worn away. Paper is discolored and fraying around edges. Ends of ribbon have begun to fray. (Box 13)
      Small, sterling silver-plated medal featuring Henry Hudson and sailors aboard “Half-Moon” on obverse. Obverse reads “Discovery of Hudson River by Henry Hudson A.D. MDCIX,” bottom left reads “The American Numismatic Society,” bottom right reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration Comm.,” bottom reads “Half Maene”. Reverse of medal depicts three female figures representing Steam Navigation, History, and Commerce below a portrait of Robert Fulton. The background features views of New York in 1807 and 1909. Reverse reads “First Use of Steam Navigation/ On The Hudson River/ 1807”. Metals designed by Emil Fuchs, whose name is signed in the bottom corner of each image on obverse and reverse. Top of medal features suspension ring. Medal attached by tri-colored (Dutch flag colors) ribbon to paper reading “Official Medal/ of the/ Hudson-Fulton/ Celebration Commission/ Patented 1909/ Published by/ The Whitehead & Hoag Co./ Newark, N.J.” Back of paper features handwritten note reading “Nyack, NY/ 1909”.
    - HF Celebration Small Silver-plated Official Suspension Medal #2, Plating has worn away in small areas where design is raised in center of faces and around edges. (Box 13)
    - HF Celebration Small Silver-plated Official Suspension Medal #3, Plating has worn away in small areas where design is raised in center of faces and around both outer edges and edges of images. (Box 13)
    - HF Celebration Small Silver-plated Official Suspension Medal #4 (Box 13)
    - HF Celebration Small Silver-plated Official Suspension Medal #5, Plating has worn away in small areas where design is raised in center of faces and around edges. (Box 13)
    - HF Celebration Brass NYS Coat of Arms Medal, Tarnish across both faces. Toning in center and along edges of both faces. Dark areas of tarnish along top edges of both faces. (Box 13)
      Possibly brass-plated Hudson-Fulton Celebration medal featuring portraits of Hudson and Fulton on obverse. Obverse reads “Hudson-Fulton/ Celebration/ 1909.” Reverse features image of New York State Coat of Arms and reads “Excelsior’. Maker’s mark on back for Schwaab S. S. & Co. Two suspension rings at top of metal.
    - HF Celebration Bronze NYS Coat of Arms Medal, Small spots of patina across obverse and around outer edges. Large spot of patina on reverse center. Dark tarnish across both faces. (Box 13)
      Possibly bronze Hudson-Fulton Celebration medal featuring portraits of Hudson and Fulton on obverse. Obverse reads “Hudson-Fulton/ Celebration/ 1909.” Reverse features image of New York State Coat of Arms and reads “Excelsior’. Maker’s mark on back for Schwaab S. S. & Co. Two suspension rings at top of metal.
    - HF Celebration Large Aluminum Official Medal, Very small spot of potential tarnish on obverse center right and on lower right outer edge. (Box 13)
      Medium-sized, aluminum medal featuring Henry Hudson and sailors aboard “Half-Moon” on obverse. Obverse reads “Discovery of Hudson River by Henry Hudson A.D. MDCIX,” bottom left reads “The American Numismatic Society,” bottom right reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration Comm.,” bottom reads “Half Maene”. Reverse of medal depicts three female figures representing Steam Navigation, History, and Commerce below a portrait of Robert Fulton. The background features views of New York in 1807 and 1909. Reverse reads “First Use of Steam Navigation/ On The Hudson River/ 1807”. Metals designed by Emil Fuchs, whose name is signed in the bottom corner of each image on obverse and reverse. “Whitehead-Hoag” stamped along bottom outer edge.
    - HF Celebration Large Aluminum Official Medal #2, Various faint scratches across both faces. (Box 13)
    - HF Celebration Large Aluminum Official Medal #3, Various faint scratches across both faces. Ends of ribbon frayed. (Box 13)
    - HF Celebration Silver-plated Official Medal, Tarnish across both faces. Small spots where plating has worn away along outer edges. (Box 13)
      Silver-plated medal featuring Henry Hudson and sailors aboard “Half-Moon” on obverse. Obverse reads “Discovery of Hudson River by Henry Hudson A.D. MDCIX,” bottom left reads “The American Numismatic Society,” bottom right reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration Comm.,” bottom reads “Half Maene”. Reverse of medal depicts three female figures representing Steam Navigation, History, and Commerce below a portrait of Robert Fulton. The background features views of New York in 1807 and 1909. Reverse reads “First Use of Steam Navigation/ On The Hudson River/ 1807”. Metals designed by Emil Fuchs, whose name is signed in the bottom corner of each image on obverse and reverse. “Whitehead-Hoag” and “Sterling” stamped along bottom outer edge.
    - HF Celebration Large Silver-plated Official Medal, Tarnish across both faces. Small spots/speckles along outer edges where plating has begun to wear. Small dark spot of tarnish on reverse top right. (Box 13)
      Large, silver-plated medal featuring Henry Hudson and sailors aboard “Half-Moon” on obverse. Obverse reads “Discovery of Hudson River by Henry Hudson A.D. MDCIX,” bottom left reads “The American Numismatic Society,” bottom right reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration Comm.,” bottom reads “Half Maene”. Reverse of medal depicts three female figures representing Steam Navigation, History, and Commerce below a portrait of Robert Fulton. The background features views of New York in 1807 and 1909. Reverse reads “First Use of Steam Navigation/ On The Hudson River/ 1807”. Metals designed by Emil Fuchs, whose name is signed in the bottom corner of each image on obverse and reverse. “Whitehead-Hoag” and “Sterling” stamped along bottom outer edge.
    - HF Celebration Large Bronze Plated Official Medal, Most of plating has worn away along outer edges revealing patinaed metal beneath. (Box 13)
      Large, bronze plated medal featuring Henry Hudson and sailors aboard “Half-Moon” on obverse. Obverse reads “Discovery of Hudson River by Henry Hudson A.D. MDCIX,” bottom left reads “The American Numismatic Society,” bottom right reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration Comm.,” bottom reads “Half Maene”. Reverse of medal depicts three female figures representing Steam Navigation, History, and Commerce below a portrait of Robert Fulton. The background features views of New York in 1807 and 1909. Reverse reads “First Use of Steam Navigation/ On The Hudson River/ 1807”. Metals designed by Emil Fuchs, whose name is signed in the bottom corner of each image on obverse and reverse. “Whitehead-Hoag” stamped along bottom outer edge.
    - HF Celebration Large Bronze Official Medal, Tarnish across both faces. Various darker spots of tarnish across obverse left. Small darker spot of tarnish on reverse right edge. Small chips in outer edge bottom center. (Box 13)
    - HF Society of Colonial Wars Ribbon, Small stain on upper right edge of front. Ribbon is frayed along bottom. Gilding is discolored and faded. Bottom right corner is creased. (Box 13)
      Red ribbon featuring golden bar across top and gilded lettering. Top banner reads “The Society of Colonial Wars/ In The State Of New York.” Front design also features society’s seal above banner reading “Hudson-Fulton/ Celebration.” Back features pin attached to ribbon.
    - HF Saint Nicholas Society Ribbon, Bottom of ribbon frayed. Right edge of top bar fraying. Small stains across reverse of top bar. (Box 13)
      Orange ribbon featuring golden bar across top and silver lettering and design. Top banner reads “The Saint Nicholas Society/ Of The City Of New York”. Bottom banner reads “Hudson-Fulton/ Celebration/ 1909.” Back features pin attached to ribbon.
    - HF Albany, NY Bronze Citizens Badge, Faint toning across obverse of medal. Brooch missing from reverse of top bar. Discoloration where brooch once was. (Box 14)
      Bronze citizens’ badge pin for the Hudson-Fulton Celebration in Albany, NY. Medal suspended from badge features portrait of Hudson and Fulton on obverse and Albany, NY Coat of Arms on reverse. Obverse reads “Hudson Fulton/ 1609-1909” and reverse reads “City of Albany/ 1909/ Hudson-Fulton Celebration.” Top bars read “Albany, NY/ 1909/ Hudson-Fulton Celebration” and “Citizens”.
    - HF Albany, NY Silver-Plated Citizens Badge, Plating on medal has worn in small spots on obverse top right. Very small spots of patina on top bars—predominantly along edges. Large area of patina on reverse of top bar where brooch is missing. Toning across reverse of very top bar. Tarnish along reverse of center bar and medal. (Box 14)
      Silver-plated and copper citizens’ badge pin for the Hudson-Fulton Celebration in Albany, NY. Silver-plated medal suspended from badge features portrait of Hudson and Fulton on obverse and Albany, NY Coat of Arms on reverse. Obverse reads “Hudson Fulton/ 1609-1909” and reverse reads “City of Albany/ 1909/ Hudson-Fulton Celebration.” Top bars read “Albany, NY/ 1909/ Hudson-Fulton Celebration” and “Citizens”.
    - HF Albany, NY Bronze and Silver-plated Naval Parades Badge, Tarnish around edges of obverse of coin and more predominantly along reverse edges of medal and top bars. Tarnish across obverse of center bar. Potential patina or corrosion below brooch on revers of very top bar. Small stains along top left of reverse of center bar. (Box 14)
      Bronze and silver-plated Naval Parades badge pin for the Hudson-Fulton Celebration in Albany, NY. Silver-plated medal suspended from badge features portrait of Hudson and Fulton on obverse and Albany, NY Coat of Arms on reverse. Obverse reads “Hudson Fulton/ 1609-1909” and reverse reads “City of Albany/ 1909/ Hudson-Fulton Celebration.” Top bars read “Albany, NY/ 1909/ Hudson-Fulton Celebration” and “Naval Parades”.
    - HF Albany, NY Silver-Plated Commemorative Exercises Badge, Most plating on medal has worn away, leaving only very small spots across obverse and around outer edges. Patina or possible corrosion present where brooch is missing. (Box 14)
      Silver-plated and copper commemorative exercises badge pin for the Hudson-Fulton Celebration in Albany, NY. Silver-plated medal suspended from badge features portrait of Hudson and Fulton on obverse and Albany, NY Coat of Arms on reverse. Obverse reads “Hudson Fulton/ 1609-1909” and reverse reads “City of Albany/ 1909/ Hudson-Fulton Celebration.” Top bars read “Albany, NY/ 1909/ Hudson-Fulton Celebration” and “Commemorative Exercises”.
    - HF Albany, NY Silver-Plated Aquatic Sports Badge, Most plating has worn away on medal, leaving on small areas on both obverse and reverse with silver-plating. Tarnish across revers of both top bars. Toning on right of reverse of very top bar. Faint tarnish across obverse of both top bars. (Box 14)
      Silver-plated and copper aquatic sports badge pin for the Hudson-Fulton Celebration in Albany, NY. Silver-plated medal suspended from badge features portrait of Hudson and Fulton on obverse and Albany, NY Coat of Arms on reverse. Obverse reads “Hudson Fulton/ 1609-1909” and reverse reads “City of Albany/ 1909/ Hudson-Fulton Celebration.” Top bars read “Albany, NY/ 1909/ Hudson-Fulton Celebration” and “Aquatic Sports”.
    - HF Albany, NY Silver-Plated Celebration Medal, Most silver-plating has worn away on medal, leaving only very small areas where portraits are raised that still contain silver. Faint tarnish across base metal on both faces. (Box 14)
      Silver-plated celebration medal for the Hudson-Fulton Celebration in Albany, NY. Medal features portrait of Hudson and Fulton on obverse and Albany, NY Coat of Arms on reverse. Obverse reads “Hudson Fulton/ 1609-1909” and reverse reads “City of Albany/ 1909/ Hudson-Fulton Celebration.”
    - HF Albany, NY Bronze Badge, Top bars for badge are missing. Only bottom medal remains. Tarnish across both faces. Small spot of patina on obverse top left. Various spots of patina on reverse center to left. (Box 14)
      Potential bronze badge pin for the Hudson-Fulton Celebration in Albany, NY. Medal features suspension ring where it would have been potentially attached to badge. Medal features portrait of Hudson and Fulton on obverse and Albany, NY Coat of Arms on reverse. Obverse reads “Hudson Fulton/ 1609-1909” and reverse reads “City of Albany/ 1909/ Hudson-Fulton Celebration.”
    - HF Albany, NY Small Bronze Medal, Tarnish across both faces of medal. Ribbon discolored and ends frayed. Only small spot of silver-plating left on obverse right center outer edge. Small spot of patina along top center outer edge. (Box 14)
      Small bronze medal, previously silver-plated, with tri-colored ribbon for the Hudson-Fulton Celebration in Albany, NY. Ribbon features colors of Dutch flag. Medal suspended from ribbon features portrait of Hudson and Fulton on obverse and Albany, NY Coat of Arms on reverse. Obverse reads “Hudson Fulton/ 1609-1909” and reverse reads “City of Albany/ 1909/ Hudson-Fulton Celebration.”
    - Blue Ribbon HF Celebration Souvenir Badge, Fraying along edges of ribbon. Large tear along bottom left edge of ribbon. Metallic portion of ribbon is discolored and tarnished. Hole in top center of ribbon possibly from previous display. Staining around hole. Tarnish across both faces of pin and obverse of coin. Toning across reverse of coin. (Box 14)
      Metal pin attached to blue backing ribbon. Medal features suspended coin depicting portraits of Hudson and Fulton. Obverse of coin reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration/ New York 1909.” Top bar is in the shape of “Clermont” and reads “Souvenir.” Reverse features image of New York State Coat of Arms. Maker’s mark on reverse for Schwaab S. & S. Co. Adhesive under brooch visible on reverse of top bar. Backing ribbon features intricate, metallic knot in center of top and metallic fringe along bottom edge. Maker’s mark on label attached to back of ribbon for Keystone Ribbon Badge Co.